Summary.
Time and a little bonus.
What have we covered?
We've covered the importance of making decisions.
We all need to make decisions in life.
And there is no other place more important than making decisions in your code.
And the way we do it in Python is using the if statement.
So very simple.
It's if some condition is true, then something will happen after that.
But we saw that we needed more than just an if statement.
We looked at how you could have an if and an else statement.
And we move beyond that, saying, well, sometimes you have multiple statements that need to be evaluated
if they're true.
So we had if and then else if that's just abbreviated to Elif, sort of like an elephant.
So in this last example we looked at, we could check multiple ranges of things of ages, and we then
pushed it further to say, well, you can also have boolean operators, which means you're actually
starting to use Ands and ORS to combine multiple variable checks.
So we could check an age greater than six or less than 13.
And another variable which was member, which is a boolean variable which can have only a true or false
value.
So we now end up with a condition that is checking three different things, and all of them will be
the culmination of all of them together.
Must evaluate to true before the statement that is indented is executed.
So price is $5 will only be printed if the age that is selected is between the range of six and lower
than 13.
And they are not a member.
Now, on that point of saying and they are not a member, there's actually another little shortcut you
can do.
So you'll see at the moment we've mentioned that member is a special type of variable.
It's a boolean can only have a true or false.
You don't actually need to write out false and true.
There is another way in which you can do this.
We wanted to show you that way first, so it makes sense.
But there is a slightly shortcut way which is better to use as long as you know what you're doing,
which you do.
In order to use that shortcut way, we have to backspace Base.
This condition here where we have said, is it equal to false?
And instead all we have to write is this word not.
So this actually reads more like an English sentence if you think about it.
So it's checking if the age is between this and if this person is not a member.
So instead of writing like we had here, is it equal to false.
Which is the same thing as saying is this person not a member?
We can basically just tap and not member.
And again we can change it here.
So this makes it a little bit easier in a sense to read.
And it's obviously shorter notation.
But you just need to understand what you're actually saying here.
So what we're going to have to do now the last one saying member is equal to true.
You can just remove it totally.
Now your reads make sense.
Is the age greater than 60 or member that means is member true.
So how this program is now going to work.
It's just going to see okay members equal to true when it comes to here, it's going to say what is
member?
Member is true.
So it is not true which is equal to false.
And this condition won't occur.
The same here.
Something that is not true is false.
So that doesn't happen.
And then here it comes.
And it says oh member is true.
So obviously this condition is true.
And it will print this.
And.
Well that would obviously happen if this person is indeed a member.
Yeah.
So the other way if.
You find this a little bit confusing, by all means carry on using and saying member equals false or.
Member equals true.
And you can check that.
But if you're comfortable with just simply saying.
Not and the Boolean variable or just the Boolean variable by itself indicate that it's true, then you
can do that as well.
But again start slowly.
Make sure you understand what you're doing.
This has been a very exciting section on how to make decisions in life, and there's some exercises
to follow.
So do those get involved?
Because as we've said before, you learn in the doing.